OMAR KARLSSON, PHD

Duke University Population Research Institute

Duke Global Health Institute

Omar.Karlsson@Duke.edu

https://OmarKarlsson.com

+1 857 415 8473

Ten years of research experience using econometrics, demographic methods, and GIS on surveys and demographic data. Over 30 peer-reviewed articles in medical, public health, and demography journals since 2019. Expert user of Stata. Experienced user of JavaScript (D3), Excel, R, and Python. Excellent written and verbal communication skills.

EXPERIENCE

2022 - now Visiting Research Fellow

Duke University Population Research Institute

Duke Global Health Institute, USA

2022 – now Postdoctoral Fellow

Centre for Economic Demography, School of Economics and Management,

Lund University, Sweden

2019 – 2022 Takemi Research Fellow in International Health

Harvard TH Chan School of Public Health, USA

2020 – 2021 External Consultant

UNICEF, Programme Division, Nutrition Section, USA

2018 - 2019 Researcher

Centre for Economic Demography, School of Economics and Management,

Lund University, Sweden

EDUCATION

2014 – 2018 PhD in Economic History

School of Economics and Management, Lund University, Sweden

Dissertation: Growth and Survival: Child Health Disparities and Early Life

Adversity in Sub-Saharan Africa

Supervisor: Martin Dribe. Assistant supervisor: Therese Nilsson

2012 – 2014 MSc in Economic Demography

School of Economics and Management, Lund University, Sweden

OTHER ACADEMIC EXPERIENCES

2016 – 2017 Visiting Graduate Student

Harvard TH Chan School of Public Health, USA

2013 Intern

Estonian Institute for Population Studies, Tallinn University

2011 – 2012 Student Exchange

Vilnius University, Lithuania

2010 **Student Exchange**

American University in Bulgaria

SELECTED LECTURES AND SEMINARS

- 2023 Korea University: International Symposium on Precision Public Health. *Differences in child mortality and morbidity across the first five years in low- and middle-income countries.*
- 2021 UNICEF: Nutrition Master Class. To what extent is child mortality and wasting prevalence concentrated before age two? Implications for nutrition and health programs
- 2020 Harvard Center for Population and Development Studies: Friday Luncheon Seminars. Household technology and child health

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

Norheim OF, Chang AY, Bolongaita S, Barraza-Lloréns L, Fawole A, Gebremedhin LD, González Pier E, Jha P, Johnson E, **Karlsson O**, Kiros, M, Lewington S, Mao W, Ogbuoji O, Pate M, Sargent J, Tang X, Watkins D, Yamey G, Yip W, Jamison D & Peto R (forthcoming). Halving premature death and improving the quality of life at all ages. *The Lancet*.

Karlsson O, Kim R, Joe W & Subramanian SV (forthcoming). International Trends in Zinc Treatment for Diarrhea. *Pediatrics*.

Jamison DT, Summers LH, Chang AY, **Karlsson O**, Mao W, Norheim OF, Ogbuoji O, Schäferhoff M, Watkins D, Adeyi O, Alleyne G, Alwan A, Anand S, Nigatu Belachew R, Berkley S, Bertozzi S, Bolongaita S, Bundy D, ... & Yamey G (2024). Global health 2050: the road to halving premature death by mid-century. *The Lancet*, 404(10462), 1561–1614. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01439-9

Karlsson O, Rajpal S, Johri M, Kim R & Subramanian SV (2024). Prevalence and Trends of Not Receiving a Dose of DPT-Containing Vaccine Among Children 12-35 Months: An

Analysis of 81 Low- And Middle-Income Countries. *Journal of Epidemiology and Global Health*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s44197-024-00294-6

Karlsson O, Benski C Kapoor M, Kim R & Subramanian SV (2024). Association between neonatal mortality and births not weighed among 400 thousand institutional deliveries in 32 low- and middle-income countries. *Journal of Public Health*. https://doi.org/10.1093/pubmed/fdae249

Karlsson O & De Neve J-W (2024). Washing machine ownership and girls' school attendance: A cross-sectional analysis of adolescents in 19 middle-income countries. *The Journal of Economic Inequality*, 1–21.

Karlsson O, Kim R & Subramanian SV (2024). Prevalence of Children Aged 6 to 23 Months Who Did Not Consume Animal Milk, Formula, or Solid or Semisolid Food During the Last 24 Hours Across Low-and Middle-Income Countries. *JAMA Network Open*, 7(2), e2355465–e2355465.

De Neve J-W, **Karlsson O**, Rai RK, Kumar S & Vollmer S (2024). Relationship between adolescent anemia and school attendance observed during a nationally representative survey in India. *Communications Medicine*, 4(1), 112.

Karlsson O & Subramanian SV (2023). Refrigerator ownership and child health and nutrition in low-and middle-income countries. *Global Food Security*, 37, 100698.

Karlsson O, Kim R, Moloney GM, Hasman A & Subramanian SV (2023). Patterns in child stunting by age: A cross-sectional study of 94 low-and middle-income countries. *Maternal & Child Nutrition*, e13537.

Subramanian SV, Khailkar A & **Karlsson O** (2023). Should India adopt a country-specific growth reference to measure undernutrition among its children? *The Lancet Regional Health - Southeast Asia*, 9. **[Comment]**

Karlsson O & Dribe M (2022). Maternal height and child health and schooling in sub-Saharan Africa: Decomposition and heterogeneity. *Social Science & Medicine*, 315, [115480].

Karlsson O. Scarring and selection effects on children surviving elevated rates of postneonatal mortality in sub-Saharan Africa (2022). *SSM - Population Health*, 19, 101160

Karlsson O, Kim R, Hasman A & Subramanian SV Age Distribution of All-Cause Mortality Among Children Younger Than 5 Years in Low- and Middle-Income Countries (2022). *JAMA Network Open*, 5(5), e2212692-e2212692.

Dribe M & **Karlsson O** (2022). Inequality in early life: Social class differences in childhood mortality in southern Sweden, 1815–1967. *Economic History Review*, 75(2), 475–502.

Karlsson O, Kim R, Guerrero S, Hasman A & Subramanian SV (2022). Child wasting before and after age two years: A cross-sectional study of 94 countries. E *Clinical Medicine*, 46, 101353.

Subramanian SV, **Karlsson O &** Kim R (2022). Using height-adjusted stunting prevalence will fail disadvantaged children worldwide, authors reply. *The Lancet Global Health*, 10(5), e621. **[Correspondence]**

Subramanian SV, **Karlsson O &** Kim R (2022). Revisiting the stunting metric for monitoring and evaluating nutrition policies. *The Lancet Global Health*, 10(2), e179-e180. **[Comment]**

Karlsson O, Domingue BW, Kim R & Subramanian SV (2022). Estimating heritability of height without zygosity information for twins under five years in low- and middle-income countries: An application of normal finite mixture distribution models. *SSM - Population Health*, 17, 101043.

Karlsson O, Kim R, Hasman A & Subramanian SV (2022). Consumption of Vitamin-A-Rich Foods and Vitamin A Supplementation for Children under Two Years Old in 51 Low-and Middle-Income Countries. *Nutrients*, 14(1), 188.

Karlsson O, Kim R, Bogin B & Subramanian SV (2022). Maternal height-standardized prevalence of stunting in 67 low- and- middle-income countries. *Journal of Epidemiology*, 32(7), 337.

Egbewale BE, **Karlsson O &** Sudfeld CR (2022). Childhood Diarrhea Prevalence and Uptake of Oral Rehydration Solution and Zinc Treatment in Nigeria. *Children*, 9(11).

Karlsson O, Kim R, Sarwal R, James KS & Subramanian SV (2021). Trends in underweight, stunting, and wasting prevalence and inequality among children under three in Indian states, 1993–2016. *Scientific Reports*, 11(1), 1-11.

Karlsson O, Dribe M & Subramanian SV (2021). Changing speed of reduction in under-5 mortality rates over the 20th century. *Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health*, 75(1), 36-39.

Li Z, **Karlsson O**, Kim R & Subramanian SV (2021). Distribution of under-5 deaths in the neonatal, postneonatal, and childhood periods: a multicountry analysis in 64 low-and middle-income countries. *International journal for equity in health*, 20 (1), 1-11.

Thoma B, Sudharsanan N, **Karlsson O**, Joe W, Subramanian SV & De Neve J-W (2021). Children's education and parental old-age health: Evidence from a population-based, nationally representative study in India. *Population Studies*, 75(1), 51-66.

Karlsson O, Kim R, Joe W & Subramanian SV (2020). The relationship of household assets and amenities with child health outcomes: An exploratory cross-sectional study in India 2015–2016. *SSM-Population Health*, 10, 100513.

Kitara DL & **Karlsson O** (2020). The effects of economic stress and urbanization on driving behaviours of Boda-boda drivers and accidents in Gulu, Northern Uganda: a qualitative view of drivers. *The Pan African Medical Journal*, 36.

Subramanian SV, Chatterjee P & **Karlsson O** (2020). Lessons from COVID-19 pandemic for the child survival agenda. *Journal of Global Health*, 10(2). **[Comment]**

Subramanian SV, **Karlsson O**, Zhang W & Kim R (2020). Geo-mapping of COVID-19 Risk Correlates Across Districts and Parliamentary Constituencies in India. *Harvard Data Science Review*, (Special Issue 1).

Teufel F, Geldsetzer P, Manne-Goehler J, **Karlsson O**, Koncz V, Deckert A, Theilmann M, Marcus ME, Ebert C, Seiglie JA, Agoudavi K, Andall-Brereton G, Gathecha G, Gurung MS, Guwatudde D, Houehanou C, Hwalla N, Kagaruki GB, Karki KB ... De Neve J-W (2020). Analysis of Attained Height and Diabetes Among 554,122 Adults Across 25 Low- and Middle-Income Countries. *Diabetes Care*, 43(10), 2403.

De Neve J-W, **Karlsson O**, Canavan CR, Chukwu A, Adu-Afarwuah S, Bukenya J, Darling AM, Harling G, Moshabela M, Killewo J ... Berhane Y (2020). Are out-of-school adolescents at higher risk of adverse health outcomes? Evidence from 9 diverse settings in sub-Saharan Africa. *Tropical Medicine & International Health*, *25*(1), 70–80.

Karlsson O (2019). Religion and Child Health in West and Central Africa. *Population and Development Review*, *45*(4), 707–738.

Karlsson O, De Neve J-W & Subramanian SV (2019). Weakening association of parental education: Analysis of child health outcomes in 43 low- and middle-income countries. *International Journal of Epidemiology, 48*(1), 83–97.

Karlsson O, Kim R, Joe W & Subramanian SV (2019). Socioeconomic and gender inequalities in neonatal, postneonatal and child mortality in India: A repeated cross-sectional study, 2005–2016. *Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health*, 73(7), 660–667.

De Neve J-W, **Karlsson O**, Coetzee L, Schröder H, Subramanian SV, Bärnighausen T & Vollmer S (2018). Antiretroviral therapy coverage associated with increased co-residence between older and working-age adults in Africa. *Aids*, *32*(14), 2051–2057.

SELECTED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

- 2024 Consortium of Universities for Global Health 15th Annual Conference. *Life* expectancy deficits by cause of death: a life table decomposition.
- The Population Association of America 2023 Annual Meeting. *Anemia severity and school attendance among 251,401 adolescents aged 15–18 years: a nationally representative household fixed-effects study in India.*
- 2018 European Population Conference. *Influence of Disease Environment in Infancy on Childhood Health and Education in Sub-Saharan Africa*.

2015 The Union for African Population Studies 7th Africa Population Conference, South Africa. *Intergenerational transmission of Capabilities: Mothers and Children in sub-Saharan Africa*.

STUDENT SUPERVISION

- 2018 Assistant Supervisor. MSc Thesis in Economic Demography from Lund University by Momoko Nishikido. *Does intimate partner violence affect contraceptive use among married women in Cambodia?* Principal Supervisor: Jeffrey Neilson. Examiner: Maria Stanfors
- 2016 Assistant Supervisor. MSc Thesis in Economic Demography from Lund University by Angelica Harryson. *The Demographic Dividend and Institutions: A Comparison between Asia and Latin America.* Principal Supervisor: Kirk Scott. Examiner: Bjorn Eriksson
- 2016 Assistant Supervisor. MSc Thesis in Economic Demography from Lund University by James Austen. Female Genital Mutilation in Senegal: The Role of Socio-Economic Risk Factors of Circumcision and Subsequent Effects of Circumcision upon Fertility and Marriage Market. Main Supervisor: Luciana Quaranta. Examiner: Martin Dribe

GRANTS

2020	Swedish Research Council International Postdoc (three-year postdoctoral scholarship)
2020	Handelsbanken Wallander Scholarship (three-year postdoctoral scholarship)
2016	Handelsbanken Hedelius Scholarship. Grant for a 12-month stay at Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health
2015	Knut and Alice Wallenberg Foundations. Grant for the 7th African Population Conference
2013	Erasmus Placement. Grant for a 3-month internship at Tallinn University
2011	Nordplus Exchange. Grant for 10-month exchange studies at Vilnius University
2010	Erasmus Exchange. Grant for 5-month exchange studies at The American University in Bulgaria